((賀兵衛:世の中には
知らぬほうが いいこともある))
♪♪～
There're things in this world you're better off not knowing about.
[Gin-san's illegitimate child is revealed! Or so we thought. The case escalates to the matter of the child being the heir of a wealthy merchant.]
[Ofusa, the mother of baby Kanshichiro. Kahei Hashidaya, a truly dangerous man.]
(長谷川)すみません｡
Excuse me. I...um...have nothing to do with this, so can I go home?
僕は あの…関係ないんで➡
帰っていいですか？
(新八)神楽ちゃん！
Kagura-chan!
How would like your coffee? With sugar or milk?
(神楽)ｺｰﾋｰのほう
砂糖とﾐﾙｸ どちらで➡
お召し上がりやがりますか？
やっぱ ｺｰﾋｰは➡
But coffee tastes best with...
sugar...isn't that right?!
砂糖で ごぜえますよな！
(志士)煙幕か？
おのれ こざかしい！ ん？
A smokescreen?
You, meddling scum!
しまった！ 女が 女が逃げたぞ!!
Damn it! The woman! The woman escaped!
(賀兵衛)入り口を捜せ｡ 必ず
この部屋の中に いるはずだ！
Search the entrance! She has to be somewhere in this room!
(似蔵)煙幕ねぇ｡
A smokescreen... But it won't work against me.
(似蔵)だが 俺には関係ないね｡
(似蔵)空気の流れがおかしいな｡
There's something different about the airflow. The smoke is flowing out somewhere...
(似蔵)どこからか流れ出てるね｡
(似蔵)どこかね…？
I wonder where...
そこか｡
There...
♪♪～
(新八たち)うぉ…｡
["If You Want to See Someone, Make an Appo First"]
I said I want to meet the president.
(銀時)だから 社長に
会わせてくれって言ってんだよ｡
(受付嬢)失礼ですが ｱﾎﾟのほうは
とられて いらっしゃいますか？
Excuse me, but do you have an "apo"?
[Note: Apo is short for appointment in Japan]
何だ ｱﾎﾟって？ あっ
あれ… 北国のﾌﾙｰﾂ？
What's an "apo"? Oh, you mean that? A kind of fruit from the north?
Does the president like Fuji apples?
社長 好きなの？ 青森ｱｯﾌﾟﾙ｡
ｱｯﾌﾟﾙじゃねえよ なんで
そこだけ 英語なんだよ｡
It's not an apple. Why are you saying only certain parts in English?!
なんなんだよ
ｱｯﾌﾟﾙとかｺﾎﾞちゃんとかよ｡
Give me a break. "Apo" or Kobo-chan...
[Note: Kobo-chan is a four-cell manga on newspaper, like a comic strip.]
こっちは 社長に
会いてえだけだっつぅのにな｡
I just want to see the president.
(勘七郎)あぽっ｡
そうだよ 最近の➡
Apo.
That's right. Nowadays, you can't do anything in Japan without slogging through a mountain of red tape.
日本はな 何をするにも
いろいろ 手続きが面倒で➡
ﾌｯﾄﾜｰｸが悪い時代なんだよ｡
あ～あっ いったい 日本は➡
Ah! What's Japan coming to?!
どこへ いこうとしているのかね｡
(受付嬢たち)えっ!?
(勘七郎)ばぶ～っ｡
すみません あんまり
騒がないでいただけます？
E-Excuse me, but could you please not speak so loud?
あら？ ちょっと待って｡
Ah?
Wait a minute. That child could be the president's...
その子 ひょっとして社長の…｡
(衝撃音)
What? What is that?
なに？ 何の音？
Ah! Excuse me, but you can't go in there without permission!
(受付嬢)あっ！ ちょっと
勝手に 入っちゃ困ります｡
ちょっと!!
Please wait!
あぽ｡
なぽ｡
Apo.
Napo.
ｷﾞｬｱ～ｯ!!
もうﾀﾞﾒだ… もうﾀﾞﾒだ｡
ごめんなさい！ ごめんなさい!!
Oh, no! We're done for! I'm sorry! I'm sorry!
(長谷川)肺が… 肺が痛い｡
My lungs! My lungs hurt! It's like they're bursting! I've made up my mind!
(長谷川)張り裂けそうだ｡
俺は 決めた！ 今日で➡
From this day forth, I will quit smoking and quit hanging with you guys!
ﾀﾊﾞｺとお前らとの
つきあいをやめる｡
あれっ 神楽ちゃんは!?
Where's Kagura-chan? She's not here!
神楽ちゃんが いない！
うごごご…!!
(新八/長谷川)げっ｡
うそ!?
(長谷川)ちょっと待って…｡
No kidding...
W-Wait a minute...
まだ 僕らいるから｡
まだ 僕らいるから！
We're still here! We're still here!
待ってぇ!!
Wait!
♪♪～
なっ…｡
んな ﾊﾞｶな… 化け物か!?
Unbelievable! He's like a monster or something!
まともに やり合って
勝てる相手じゃない｡
We don't stand a chance against him! Run!!
ここは逃げましょう｡
よし｡
All right!
あれ… 最初から逃げてなかった？
Well, weren't we already running away in the beginning?
どわっ！
おっ？
ﾁｸｼｮｰ!! おいっ 大丈夫か!?
Damn it!
Hey!
Are you all right?
えっ!?
(長谷川)うわ～！
やばっ 屋根から落ちる…｡
Ah! We're gonna fall!!
(悲鳴)
(志士)なに!? 姿を消したぞ ﾔﾂら｡
What?! They disappeared! Where did they go?!
(志士)いったい どこに!? くそっ｡
Damn it! Let's check over there!
(志士)あっちを捜すぞ｡
(志士たち)おうっ！
(お房)あの 大丈夫ですか？
Um... Are you all right?
よかった… 下に屋根があって｡
What a relief! There was another roof underneath.
あぁ 小便ちびるかと思った｡
Oh, I was so scared I almost wet my pants.
あっ…｡
(お房)あの あなたたち➡
Well, who are you guys?
いったい誰なんですか？
あなたですよね？
It was you, right? The one who left the baby in front of our house?
僕らの家の前に
赤ん坊を置いてったのって｡
(長谷川)う 嘘だろう…｡
N-No kidding...
Huh? So, you guys...
(長谷川)もう38歳だぞ…｡
Don't worry. The baby has been taken into protective custody.
I'm 38 already ...
(お房)ﾎﾝﾄですか!? 勘七郎は…｡
Really?! Kanshichiro... Kanshichiro is safe?!
(お房)勘七郎は無事なんですね!?
あっ！ 掃除してた
ときに ついたんだ｡
Oh, I must have gotten this while cleaning! So if I take off my apron...
Whoa! Hey, hey! Calm down. Please calm down!
(長谷川)ｴﾌﾟﾛﾝをとれば…｡
やっぱり あなたが
あの子の母親なんですね｡
You're the baby's mother, right?
何があったか教えてくれますか？
Can you tell us what happened? I think we have the right to know at least.
それくらい 聞く権利
ありますよね 僕らにも｡
I was from a poor family,
(お房)家が貧しかった私は➡
昔 この橋田屋に使用人として➡
So I was sent to work as a servant here at the Hashidaya.
奉公していたんです｡
(お房)私の仕事は
旦那様のご子息…➡
My job was to take care of the master's son, Kantaro-sama, who was sickly and bedridden.
病弱で 寝たきりの➡
勘太郎様のお世話でした｡
((お房:あの… お房でございます｡
Um... I'm Ofusa... I'm honored to be working for you.
よろしくお願いします｡
(勘太郎)あぁ 新しい使用人か｡
Ah, you're the new servant. Nice to...
よろしく… ｶﾞﾊｯ｡
ｷｬｰ！ 誰か来てっ!!
Somebody help! Somebody!
(お房)誰か！ 誰か!!
Somebody, please!
ｱﾊﾊﾊ… 驚いたか ﾄﾞｯｷﾘだ！
[Surprise!]
Gotcha! That was a surprise!
(お房)誰か来て！ 勘太郎様が!!
Somebody help!! Kantaro-sama is... Kantaro-sama is...!
(お房)勘太郎様が!!
(勘太郎)あの ちょっと これ｡
Well...hey...look over here...
(お房)勘太郎様が死にました！
Kantaro-sama is dead!
(勘太郎)いや…
違うんだって ちょっと これ｡
No, I'm not. Hey, over here...
誰か～っ！
Someone!
Hey! Are you listening to me?!
ちょっと これ 聞いてる!?))
Kantaro-sama loved to joke around. And he often played tricks on his servants.
(お房)勘太郎様は
ｲﾀｽﾞﾗ好きな方で➡
よく使用人たちをからかい➡
みんなを困らせていました｡
(お房)でも 私のような者にも➡
But he was also a very kind person, who treated me like a friend.
まるで 友人のように
接してくれる優しい人で…｡
(お房)私は だんだんと➡
And I gradually grew attracted to him.
あの人に惹かれていきました｡
Ofusa, how much longer do I have to stay bedridden?
((勘太郎:お房よ
ｵﾚは いつまで➡
こうして寝たきりで
過ごさなきゃならんのだろう？
There you go again. You've been coughing a lot today, so you can't go for a walk.
(お房)ま～た 始まった｡
今日は咳もひどいし
お散歩は ﾀﾞﾒですよ｡
ｵﾚは どうせ
長生きできないだろう？
I know I won't live very long. Well, if I live lazy like this, I might live a bit longer.
そりゃ こうして
ｸﾞｰﾀﾗ過ごしてりゃ➡
少しは長く
生きられるかもしれんが｡
そんなこと おっしゃっては
旦那様が悲しまれます｡
The master would be sad to hear you say that.
旦那様は 勘太郎様のご病気を
治そうと 必死なんですよ｡
Master is trying very hard to cure your illness, Kantaro-sama.
(勘太郎)あの ｵｯｻﾝはな
ｵﾚに この橋田屋を継がせて➡
That old man just wants me to succeed him to protect his fortune.
財産を守りたいだけだっつ～の｡
(勘太郎)財産とか
長いこと生きるとか➡
Fortune and living a long life... Are they really that important?
そんなに大事なことかねぇ…？
それは…
私には ﾜｶﾞﾏﾏに聞こえます｡
It sounds to me like you're being selfish.
すべて持っている人の ﾜｶﾞﾏﾏに｡
そうかもな｡
It's the selfishness of someone who already has everything.
Maybe so.
だったら いっそ ｵﾚは
何もいらないからさ｡
If that's the case, I don't need anything.
そうさな…➡
Let's say...
I'd rather be like a cherry blossom.
桜の花にでもなりたいね｡
(お房)桜の花？
Cherry blossom?
ｳﾌﾌ… 桜の花になったら➡
Kantaro-sama, but if you turn into a cherry blossom, you'll wither away before spring ends.
春が終わる前に
すべて散ってしまうんですよ｡
いいんだよ それで｡
えっ？
That's the way it should be.
あんなにも思いっきり➡
They're brilliant and fully bloomed, just like that.
その身を艶やかに
咲かせているじゃねえか))
Six months later, Kantaro-sama and I left the house and ran away together.
(お房)それから半年後
私と勘太郎様は➡
２人隠れて
逃げるように屋敷から出ました｡
私… 勘太郎様の
力になりたかったんです｡
I knew it was wrong, but I wanted to make Kantaro-sama happy.
(お房)そして
一緒に暮らしはじめて➡
We started living together.
生活は苦しかったけど
一生懸命 働いて➡
Our lives were difficult, but we worked really hard.
泣いたり 笑ったり 楽しかった｡
Crying and laughing... We were so happy... However...
でも…｡
((ﾊｧ… ﾊｧ…｡
ようやく見つけたと思ったら
このｻﾞﾏだ｡
I finally track you down and look at you.
私のもとに
おとなしくしていれば➡
If you had stayed home and kept to your bed like I told you to,
your illness wouldn't have taken a turn for the worse.
こんなに病が
悪化することもなかったのに！
こんな汚い女に
たぶらかされおって｡
You were deceived by that nasty woman.
(賀兵衛)すべて ｷｻﾏのせいだ｡
This is all your fault! Anyway, I'm taking Kantaro back home.
とにかく勘太郎は連れて帰るぞ｡
あっ…！
(お房)待ってください旦那様！
(賀兵衛)うるさい!!
Please wait, Master!
Shut up!
(お房)ああっ！
(叩く音)
It can't be... You're carrying... Kantaro's...
まさかｷｻﾏ 腹に勘太郎の…！
おろせ｡
Abort it. If word of this got out, the family name would be tarnished.
妙なｳﾜｻを立てられると
橋田家の名に傷がつくわ！))
♪♪～
(お房)その後 私と勘太郎様は➡
After that, Kantaro-sama and I were not allowed to see each other anymore.
最後まで
会うことを許されませんでした｡
あの人が亡くなるまで…｡
Until he passed away...
ほどなくして 勘七郎が生まれ➡
Then Kanshichiro was born.
私 あの人の分も
立派に育てようと決心しました｡
I decided to do my best to raise him.
♪♪～
(戸が開く音)
((お房:旦那様!?))
Master!
(お房)ただ１人の
ご子息を失った旦那様は➡
Master had lost his only son, so he had his eye on Kanshichiro as his heir.
跡取りにと
勘七郎に目をつけたのです｡
I lost Kantaro-sama,
(お房)あの人を失い
さらに勘七郎まで失うのは➡
and I couldn't stand losing Kanshichiro, too.
私 耐えられなくて…｡
でも 追っ手の勢いが厳しく➡
But they kept chasing me.
このままでは
親子２人 捕まってしまうと…｡
And I knew it was only a matter of time before Kanshichiro and I were captured.
♪♪～
(志士たちの怒声)
((ごめんね 必ず迎えにくるから｡
I'm sorry, but I'll come back for you...
ごめんね… ごめんね！))
I'm sorry.
(志士たちの声)
Please forgive me...
あなたたちには➡
すまないことをしたと
思っています｡
私の勝手な都合で
こんなことに巻き込んでしまって｡
I feel sorry about what I did. I got you guys involved in this for my own selfish reasons.
お房ちゃん… ｱﾝﾀ若いのに
苦労したんだねぇ｡
Ofusa-chan, you're a young woman whose had a tough life, huh?
But it sounds like that bastard Kahei is a real lowlife.
(長谷川)しかし賀兵衛って野郎は
とんでもない ｹﾞｽ野郎らしい｡
That woman is the lowlife.
(賀兵衛)ｹﾞｽは そこの女だ！
That wench killed my only son.
息子を殺したのは
紛れもなく その女｡
ｿｲﾂさえいなければ
橋田屋は安泰だった｡
If it weren't for her, my company would be secure.
(賀兵衛)勘太郎に
私の跡を継がせ➡
I planned for Kantaro to become my heir and then my life's work would've been complete.
私の生涯の仕事は
完遂するはずだったんだ｡
それを 貧しく卑しい女に
台なしにされたんだ｡
But that vulgar, lowborn woman ruined everything.
私が これまで➡
Do you have any idea what I endured for the sake of this company?
どんな思いをして この橋田屋を
守ってきたか わかるか？
泥水をすすり
汚いことに手を染め➡
I groveled in the mud, I hobnobbed with human scum, I even betrayed my own conscience.
両親さえ捨てて
この店を守ってきた｡
(賀兵衛)この私の気持が
わかるか!?
Can you understand my feelings?!
勘太郎様は あなたの
そういうところを嫌っていました｡
Kantaro-sama hated that part of you.
(お房)なぜそんなに
この店に執着するのですか？
Why are you so obsessed with this business? Is it money? Or power?
お金ですか？ 権力ですか!?
(賀兵衛)ﾌﾝ！
女 子供にはわかるまい！
Humph! A woman like you will never understand...
(長谷川/お房)あっ…｡
ああっ！
(賀兵衛)男は その生涯をかけて
１つの芸術品を作る｡
A man spends his entire life trying to create a single work of art.
芸術といっても
人によって それは千差万別｡
Art is infinite in variety, from one person to another and takes on many forms.
私にとって
それは橋田屋なんだよ｡
For me, it's the Hashidaya.
(賀兵衛)芸術品を
美しく仕上げるためなら➡
No matter what, I have to finish my masterwork.
私は いくらでも汚れられる｡
I will sink to any depth to protect it.
いけ!!
Go!
(志士たち)うぉ～っ！
(志士たち)わ～っ!!
Hey, is this the president's office?
お～ぅ 社長室はここかい？
な… なに!?
Wh-What?!
So, this is what...I need to see you, right?
これで面会してくれるよな？
ｱﾎﾟｰ！
(勘七郎)ﾅﾎﾟｰ！
Apo.
Napo.
♪♪～
(賀兵衛)なんだ？ ｷｻﾏ！ 何者だ!?
What? Bastard! Who the hell are you?!
あぁ!? なんだ ﾂﾐは ってか？
Huh? Who am I?
そうです!! 私が 子守り狼です！
That's right. I'm...
...a babysitting lone wolf.
銀さん！
勘七郎!!
Gin-san!
Kanshichiro!
なんか めんどくせえことに
なってんなぁ…｡
It seems things have got way more complicated here. Shinpachi, explain it in thirty words or less.
新八！ 30字以内で簡潔に述べろ!!
ﾑﾘです！
銀さんこそ どうして ここに？
That's impossible, Gin-san. Why are you here? You explain it in thirty words or less.
30字以内で
簡潔に述べてください！
ﾑﾘだ！
ｵﾒｴ ﾊﾞｶか!?
Impossible.
Are you crazy?! Why would you bring the baby into enemy territory?!
わざわざ敵陣に
赤ん坊 連れてくるﾔﾂがいるか！
What's with you? I just saved your butt.
なんだ？ ﾃﾒｴ…
人が せっかく助けてやったのに｡
っていうか なんで
こんなところにいるんだい？
What are you doing here anyway? In thirty words or less.
30字以内で簡潔に述べろ！
うるせえ！ あのじじいは
その子 狙ってんだよ!!
Shut up!
That old man is trying to steal that kid! His son knocked up the kid's mother.
(長谷川)自分の息子がはらませた
この子を足蹴にしておきながら➡
And now the old man's knocking her down.
息子が死んだら そのｶﾞｷを奪って➡
He wouldn't accept the tyke while his son was alive, but now that his son's dead...
跡取りにしようとしてんだよ！
He wants the kid to become his heir!
ん？ おいおい…｡
Hey, hey. I came here to return the kid, but I guess I'll have to change my plan.
せっかくｶﾞｷ返しに
足運んだっていうのに➡
ﾑﾀﾞ足だったみてえだな｡
(賀兵衛)ﾑﾀﾞ足ではない｡
それは 私の孫だ｡
This is nonsense! He's my grandson. He's the heir to the Hashidaya. Hand him over.
橋田屋の大事な跡取りだ！
こちらへ渡せ｡
ｵﾚは ｺｲﾂから解放されるなら➡
I really don't care whether I give you to your grandpa or your mother
じじいだろうが 母ちゃんだろうが
どっちでもいいけどな！
as long as I'm not stuck with you anymore, but...
おい ｵﾒｴは どうなんだい？
Hey, what do you think?
(勘七郎)なふ！
おぉ そうかい そうかい｡
Oh, I see, I see.
(賀兵衛)ん？
(お房)あっ!!
悪いな じいさん…｡
Sorry, old man.
He said he'd rather suck momma's flat chest than suck on your hairy old teats.
じじいの汚ねえ乳
吸うくらいなら➡
母ちゃんの貧相な乳
しゃぶってたほうがﾏｼだとよ｡
やめてくれません？
そのいやらしい表現！
Please stop! Please stop using such disgusting expressions!
やめてくれません!?
Do you think you can outrun us? We've got an ace up our sleeve.
逃げ切れると思ってるのか？
こちらには とっておきの
手駒が残っているんだぞ！
ん？
Although he's blind, he's a master of Iai.
[Note: Iai, as in Iai jutsu, are techniques for drawing a sword.]
(賀兵衛)盲目の身でありながら
居合を駆使し➡
どんな獲物も
一撃必殺で仕留める殺しの達人｡
He's also a master assassin who can kill anyone with one unstoppable blow.
(賀兵衛)その名も 岡田 似蔵…
人斬り似蔵と恐れられる男だ！
His name is Nizo Okada. Otherwise known as...Nizo the butcher.
(似蔵)やぁ
また会えると思っていたよ｡
Yo, I knew I'd see you again.
ﾃﾒｴ あのときの…
目が見えなかったのか？
I've seen you before... You were blind?!
今度は
両手が空いているようだねぇ｡
Both of your hands are free this time. I'm glad. Now we can fight for real.
嬉しいねぇ… これで心おきなく
やりあえるというもんだよ｡
(賀兵衛)似蔵…
勘七郎の所在さえわかれば➡
Nizo! As long as we have Kanshichiro, we've won half the battle! Kill them all!
こっちのもんだ！
全員 たたき斬ってしまえ!!
銀さん 気をつけてください！
Gin-san! Be careful! That guy is a master of Iai! So don't let his timing affect you!
[Note: Timing is one of the elements of Iai jutsu.]
ｿｲﾂ 居合の達人です！
絶対に
間合いに入っちゃﾀﾞﾒですよ！
♪♪～
うっ！
銀さん!!
銀ちゃん！
Gin-san!
あっ… 勘七郎が！
Kanshichiro!
(似蔵)いけないねぇ…｡
That's not good.
(似蔵)赤ん坊は
しっかり抱いておかないと…｡
You should've held on tighter to your baby.
(似蔵)ねぇ おかあさん！
(お房)勘七郎!!
Eh, Mother?
Kanshichiro!
さすがは似蔵… 恐るべき早技｡
Great job, Nizo. That was quick and fearless! I'll just sit back and enjoy the show.
あとは ゆっくり高みの見物でも
させてもらうかな｡
I'm sorry, Master... It seems I won't be able to put this guy away as easily as I thought.
悪いねぇ 旦那…｡
ｵﾚも あの男相手じゃ
そんなに余裕がないみてえだ｡
悪いが さっさとｶﾞｷ連れて
逃げてくれるかね？
Sorry, but you'd better take the child and quickly go.
(勘七郎の ぐずる声)
Kanshichiro!
(お房)勘七郎！
(賀兵衛)こら 暴れるな｡
Hey, hey! Don't move so much!
ど… どうしたというのだ？ こら｡
Wh-What's the matter?! Hey!
おいおい…
だいぶ嫌われてるんじゃねえの？
Hey, hey. He seems to hate you, doesn't he?!
ｵﾚといたときは 初めてﾃﾞｰﾄする➡
When he was with me, he was as quiet as a middle school boy on his first date.
中学男子並みに
おとなしかったぜ！ ｿｲﾂは｡
あやし方 教えてやろうか？
Should I teach you how to soothe him?
なに!?
孫っていうのは普通➡
What?!
In general, a grandchild likes his grandpa.
じいちゃんのこと
好きなもんだけどな｡
うぅっ…｡
じいちゃんの資格
ねえんじゃねえの？ ｱﾝﾀ｡
You're not qualified to be his grandpa, are you?
うるさい！ 似蔵
さっさと とどめを刺せ!!
Shut up!
Nizo!
Go for the kill!
Shinpachi, Kagura, I'll be fine. You go after the kid and the old man.
新八！ 神楽!! もういいから
ｵﾒｴらは ｶﾞｷとじじいを追いな！
でも！
いいから 行けっつうの!!
But!
Just go!
ｸｯ…｡
銀さん！
(神楽)銀ちゃん!!
Gin-chan!
Gin-san!
あとで…｡
Later...
あとで 必ず行くからよ｡
I promise to meet you later.
♪♪～
いいのかねぇ…｡
Are you sure? A samurai shouldn't make a promise he can't keep.
侍が果たせぬ約束なんぞ
するもんじゃないよ｡
心配いらねえよ…
こう見えても ｵﾚは律儀なんでね｡
No sweat. I'm more dependable than I look.
ﾃﾞｰﾄの待ち合わせ場所にも➡
I'm the type of guy who arrives for a date 30 minutes early.
30分前には
絶対 行ってるｸﾁだから｡
ｸｸｯ…
やっぱり おもしろい男だね｡
You're such a funny man, just like I thought.
(似蔵)ｵﾚは 若え頃に
病で目をやっちまったが➡
I lost my eyesight to a disease when I was young.
人間ってのはﾀﾌな生き物でねぇ…
失った目の代わりに➡
But humans are tough creatures.
The other senses grow more acute to compensate for the loss of vision.
他の器官が こぞって
穴を埋めようとしやがる｡
おかげで 今じゃ 鼻も耳も勘も
利くようになっちまって…｡
Because of that, my nose, ears and intuition have become very sharp.
ｵﾚの全身は これ目玉さね｡
My whole body works as my eye. I see the world more fully than before.
前よりも いろんなものが
見えるようになった｡
ｱﾝﾀは 見たことがあるかね？
Have you ever seen what comes out of a man the moment he dies? I wonder if it's his soul.
(似蔵)人が死ぬ瞬間に
出てくるｱﾚを…｡
(似蔵)ひょっとしたら
ｱﾚが 魂ってﾔﾂなのかね？
やった瞬間にﾎﾟﾜｯと…
これが きれいな色をしててねぇ｡
It's released at the same time I kill a person...
And it's such a beautiful color.
追いかけてたら 人斬りなんて
呼ばれるようになっちゃって…｡
So I kept chasing it, and people started calling me the butcher.
なぁ ｱﾝﾀの魂の色は何色だい？
So, what color is your soul?
ﾃﾒｴ… ｻﾝｺﾝさんより
目 いいんじゃねえの？
You... Your eyes are even better than Sankon-san's?
[Note: Osuman Youla Sankhon is a Guinean performer on Japanese TV who was known for having exceptional eyesight.]
全身目玉だか 目玉の親父だか
知らねえが➡
I don't care if your whole body is your eyeball, or that old man's eyeball.
そんな大層なもんなくても
ｵﾚには見えるぜ｡
But I don't need any special powers to see.
ﾃﾒｴの汚ねえ魂の色が！
I can see... The color of your grimy soul. It's the color of a turd.
ｳﾝｺみてえな色してるぞ！
人斬りなんぞができるﾔﾂは➡
The only kind of person who can kill people is a piece of crap
人の痛みもなにも見ようとしねえ
ｸｿ野郎だけだ！
who doesn't even try to understand the feelings of others.
全身で見えてても
ﾃﾒｴの魂は何も見えちゃいねえよ！
Even if your whole body can see, your soul can't see anything.
Want to find out?
試してみるかい？
来いよ！ 頭 叩き割ってやらあ！
Come on. I'll smash your skull into pieces!
♪♪～
You asked for it...
来いよと言うから 行ったがね…➡
Was I too fast for you? Now which one of us is blind?
ちと 速すぎたかねぇ？
見えてないのは➡
ｱﾝﾀのほうだったね｡
[Refreshing Nose]
どうした～？
ｵﾚが死ぬ幻覚でも見たかよ？
What's wrong? Did you see an illusion of me dying?
…ﾊﾞｶな！
確かに 斬り捨てたはず！
I-Impossible! I just killed him, I'm sure of it...
うっ… なんでだ!?
Wh-Why?
(似蔵)刀身が…!?
My sword blade...
抜き身も見せねえ
俊足の居合が 仇になったな｡
Your Iai was quick on the draw. But this time it worked against you.
《似蔵:まさか 最初の一撃で
すでに ｵﾚの刀は…！
It can't be! His first strike broke my blade?!
ｵﾚの俊足の抜刀術を
上回る速さで…！
He was even faster than my speedy Batto jutsu?
[Note: Batto jutsu are techniques for drawing a sword. Also called Iai jutsu.]
斬ったとみたは ｵﾚの まぶたの
裏のみだったというのか…》
I thought I cut him, but that was only in my head!
だから 言ったろ｡ ｵﾒｴの魂は
何も見えちゃいねえって！
I already told you. Your soul can't see a thing.
もうちっと 魂見開いて生きろ！
この ﾀｺｽｹ!!
A bit more...
You should open your soul and live!
(賀兵衛)ﾊｧ ﾊｧ ﾊｧ…！
S-Stay back! Kanshichiro is my grandson!
(賀兵衛)く… 来るな！
勘七郎は 私の孫だ！
(賀兵衛)この 橋田屋も
私のものだ！ 誰にも渡さんぞ！
The Hashidaya is also mine! No one can take them away from me!
(お房)橋田屋なんて
好きにしてください！
You can do whatever you like with the Hashidaya. But that child is my son.
(お房)でも その子は
私の子です！
Damn you, woman.
ｸｿ～ いまいましい女め！
私から 勘太郎を奪い➡
You took Kantaro away from me and now you're trying to take Kanshichiro and the Hashidaya away, too?
あまつさえ
勘七郎も 橋田屋までも奪う気か！
(勘七郎)うぅ…｡
H-Hey! Be quiet!
こらこら おとなしくしなさい｡
(お房)勘七郎にも➡
Kanshichiro can hear...
聞こえているんです｡
あなたの言っていることが…｡
...what you're saying.
Impossible! What can a baby like this understand?
ﾊﾞｶな！
こんな赤ん坊に なにが わかる！
わかるんですよ！
そして 覚えているんです｡
He understands. And he remembers.
どんな乳飲み子でも…➡
All babies do. Especially the memory of being held tenderly...
特に 優しく抱かれているときの
記憶は…｡
勘太郎様が
よく おっしゃっていました｡
Kantaro-sama always told me that.
(お房)そこには
たくさんの花と祭壇と➡
There was an altar covered with flowers and a picture of a beautiful woman...
きれいな女の人の写真が
飾ってあって…｡
((賀兵衛:大丈夫さ…｡
Don't worry... Everything will be all right. We'll survive somehow.
(賀兵衛)お前がいなくとも
やっていけるさ｡ 私たちは…｡
We'll be fine...
(賀兵衛)ﾒｼも 私が作るし
ｵｼﾒも…｡
I'll cook the meals and change the diapers...
Well, I don't know how to, but I'll change the diapers somehow...
(賀兵衛)まっ 勝手は わからんが
なんとか取り替える｡
(賀兵衛)だから
安心して いくといい…｡
So you can go on without a worry.
勘太郎と橋田屋は 私が守るよ))
I'll protect Kantaro and the Hashidaya.
Do you think what you're doing would make Kantaro-sama and your wife happy?
(お房)こんなことをして
勘太郎様や奥様が 喜ぶとでも？
(賀兵衛)勘太郎は
生まれたときから 病弱だった…｡
Kantaro was born sickly.
The doctor said he would, at the most, live one-third a normal lifetime.
(賀兵衛)長生きしても
人の ３分の１が➡
いいところだと
医者に言われてな…｡
After hearing that, my wife said that we would make him three times happier.
(賀兵衛)だが それを聞いて妻は
人の３倍 笑って➡
生きていけるように
してあげればいいと…｡
桜の花のように短くても➡
Like a cherry blossom--he can live a full life, even if it's short.
あでやかに 己を咲かせて
生きていけばいいと…｡
そんなことを言っていた…｡
But I wasn't as clever as my wife.
だが 私は
妻ほど 利口じゃなくてな｡
医者を 腐るほど雇って➡
I hired all the doctors I could and raised my son like a bird in a cage.
まるで 檻にでも入れたように
勘太郎を育てた…｡
(賀兵衛)どんな形でも
生きていてほしかった…｡
I wanted them alive in any way possible. My wife...
(賀兵衛)妻にも 勘太郎にも…｡
And Kantaro...
Now, I've lost everything. I couldn't keep any of my promises after all...
結局
みんな なくしてしまったがね…｡
結局 私は 約束をひとつも…｡
♪♪～
You haven't lost everything.
全部 なくしてなんか
ないじゃないですか｡
In fact... See?
その証拠に ほら…｡
もふっ…｡
勘七郎…｡
Kanshichiro...
Kanshichiro is my child.
(お房)勘七郎は 私の子供です｡
But he's also your grandson.
でも 紛れもなく
あなたの孫でも あるんですよ｡
So the next time you visit my house, it won't be as the master of Hashidaya,
だから 今度 家に来るときは
橋田屋の主人としてではなく➡
ただの 孫思いの
おじいちゃんとして➡
but as a grandfather who loves his grandson.
来てくださいね｡
うぅっ…｡
(お房)お茶菓子くらい
出しますから…｡
And we'll have tea and cakes together.
(賀兵衛の泣き声)
やっぱ 母親には かなわねえな｡
母は強し ってﾔﾂ？
I guess no one can beat a mother. It's like, "Mothers are strong," huh?
おい！
なんで ｵﾑﾂはいてんだ？ おい！
Hey, why are you wearing a diaper? Hey!
So, it's time for us to go home.
(お房)それじゃあ
私たちは これで…｡
本当に お世話になりました｡
Thank you so much for everything. I'll never forget what you did for us.
この ご恩は 一生 忘れません｡
Please don't remember me losing my dignity as a person.
ｵﾚが 人の尊厳 失ったことは
忘れてね｡
(笑い声)
ぷは～っ｡ どうだ？ うめえか？
How is it? Taste good?
なふっ！
なにぃ？
What? The milk isn't good enough for you?
ﾐﾙｸじゃ 物足りねえってか？
おいおい 100年 早えよ｡
Hey, hey. It's a hundred years too early for you.
酒は いろんなところに
毛が生えてから 飲むもんだ｡
You can start drinking sake after you at least grow some hair in a few places.
そうさなあ お前が
もうちょっと 大人になったら➡
Yeah... When you're a little older...
そんときに
まだ ｵﾚのことを覚えてたら…➡
...and if you still remember me.
また 会いにこい｡ そんときは
いくらでも つきあうよ｡
Come see me sometime. I'd be glad to have a drink with you.
すぷん？
あぁ 約束だ｡
Yes, you have my word. A samurai doesn't make a promise he can't keep.
侍は
果たせねえ約束は しねえんだ｡
せいぜい
いっぱい笑って いっぱい泣いて➡
Well, laugh a lot and cry a lot and grow up quick.
さっさと 大人になるこった｡
待ってるぜ！
I'll be waiting.
(泣き声)
Yeah, yeah.
What's the matter?
あら… どうしたの？
Oh, my! He's crying so hard! How strange, he hardly ever cries...
(お房)あ～
こんなに泣いちゃって…｡
(お房)おかしいわね… この子
めったに泣くことなんてないのに｡
春も じき 終わりやがるな…｡
Spring is almost over...
The next episode... "Stress Makes You Bald, but It's Stressful to Avoid Stress, so You End Up Stressed Out Anyway, so in the End There's Nothing You Can Do."
[Serial arson in Edo! Tatsumi, the female firefighter pursues the criminal.]
[These brats, who often appear, are Yo-chan and Ken-chan. Kids' annoyance factor is proportional to the length of their hair.]
(ｻｲﾎｰﾝ)ｻｲ～｡
(ﾉｯｸ)
(ｾﾚﾅ)は～い どうぞ｡
出かけるの？
ねぇねぇ どっちがいいかな？